Daniel Joseph Gomez

Biological Sciences, Graduate Student, <u>California State University</u>, <u>East Bay</u> Genetics, <u>Snyder Lab</u>, <u>Stanford Genetics</u>, <u>Stanford Medicine</u>

Address: 3165 Porter Dr

Palo Alto, CA 94304

Cell Phone: +1 (650) 201-1272 Email: <u>djgomez@stanford.edu</u> Website: danieljgomez.org

SUMMARY

Skilled Biomedical Data Scientist/Engineer with a focus on Precision Medicine, Genomics, Cancer, Immunology, Neurology, Computational Biology, and Bioinformatics. Experienced in leveraging diverse datasets to create customized interventions and therapeutic solutions, with specialized knowledge in Spatial Omics and Microscopy techniques

RESEARCH ACTIVITIES

Research Focus: Predicting disease and fitness (exercise, aptitude, physical activity) of the human body at cellular-resolution, multiomics, multi-modal omics analysis, exerkine mapping, inter-organismal (human and preclinical models), predictive biomedicine, Molecular Transducers of Physical Activity Consortium (MoTrPAC), Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) Project, Human BioMolecular Atlas Program (HuBMAP), Human Tumor Atlas Network (HTAN), spatial maps at the single-cell level, multi-tissue architecture, deep omics profiling, predictive modeling, multimodal modeling, deep learning, data integration, image segmentation, causal learning, representation learning, cell-cell communication, precision exercise medicine

Education and Training

Graduate

2022- M.S., Biological Sciences: Genomics & Computational Biology

Department of Biological Sciences

California State University, Hayward, CA

Department of Genetics

Stanford University School of Medicine, Palo Alto, CA

(Thesis Advisor: <u>Prof. Michael Snyder</u>)

Research Thesis Project: Leading a collaborative effort at Stanford University to map exercise-induced exerkines across organs using deep omics profiling and spatial omics. Integrate data from preclinical models and humans, analyzing multi-omics datasets to elucidate therapeutic implications for positive patient stratification and health outcomes. Integrate data from preclinical models and humans, analyze multi-omics datasets to collect, model, process, integrate exerkines across organ architecture or tissue microenvironments, cell/molecular networks and nuclear organization. Contribute to precision medicine by upgrading the novel multiplex imaging and analysis in intra-organ communication via spatial tissue maps with

proper cell annotation, image segmentation, clustering niches into community plots, neighborships, cell types/subtypes, and advancing single-cell and spatial omics technologies. This will provide insights about how exerkines prevents, manages, and treats disease while predicting health outcomes (patient stratification, survivability)

2024-	HuBMAP Visible Human MOOC Department of Cyberinfrastructure for Network Science Center Indiana University
2024	<u>Certificate</u> , Bioinformatics in Precision Medicine Fundamentals of Data Science in Precision Medicine and Cloud Computing Department of Genetics, Stanford University School of Medicine Stanford Data Ocean, Stanford Deep Data Research Center
2023	2nd Annual Spatial Biology Workshop (Angelo Lab) Department of Pathology, Stanford School of Medicine
2023	Graduate Student Intern (SCI Faculty Support) Department of Structural Biology, Department of Chemical and Systems Biology Stanford Cancer Institute, Stanford University School of Medicine (Advisor: <u>Prof. Kacper Rogala</u>)
2023	Image Processing Workshop for Cryo-Electron Microscopy S2C2 Stanford-SLAC Cryo-EM Center
2023	Biological cryogenic microscopy and tomography (BioE 320) Stanford Bioengineering, Schools of Engineering & Medicine (Advisor: <u>Prof. Wah Chiu</u>)
2023	Certificate, SSRL RapiData 2023: Data Collection and Structure Solving: A Practical Course in Macromolecular X-Ray Diffraction Measurement Structural Molecular Biology (SMB) Division, Macromolecular Crystallography, Stanford Synchrotron Radiation Lightsource (SSRL), SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory (Advisor: Dr. Aina Cohen)
2012-13	Neurosciences, Neurovirology Graduate Courses Department of Cell and Molecular Biology (CMB) Department of Tropical Medicine, Medical Microbiology, and Pharmacology (DTMMMP), John A. Burns School of Medicine (JABSOM), Honolulu, HI (Advisor: Prof. Dr. Bruce Shiramizu, Prof. Vivek Nerurkar)
2012	Translational Research in NeuroAIDS and Mental Health Neuroimmune Pharmacology Graduate Course Department of Neurology and Neurosurgery

Division of Neuroimmunology and Neurological Infections Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine (Advisor: Dr. Avindra Nath, Prof. Amanda Brown, Prof. Dr. Bruce Shiramizu)

Under graduate

2020-22	B.S., Cell and Molecular Biology, San Francisco State University, CA
	(Advisor: Prof. Michael Goldman, Prof. Nicole Salazar-Velmeshev)
2010-13	Molecular Cell Biology, University of Hawaii at Manoa, HI
	(Advisor: Prof. Paul Patek, Prof. Dr. Bruce Shiramizu)
2008-10	Communication Studies (Honors, Sigma Chi Eta Chapter), Ohlone College, CA
2003-09	Dual Credit (Study Abroad), Modesto Junior College, CA

Professional Experience

2023-	Graduate Student Researcher, Snyder Lab, Stanford Genetics
2023	Neuroimaging Data Scientist, Steinberg Lab, Stanford Neurosurgery
2023-	Vice President of STEM Programs, Myplaceisahappy1 (MPH1)
2023	Graduate Student Intern, Stanford Cancer Institute (SCI), Stanford Medicine
2022-23	Visiting scientist "User", SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory
2022-23	Teaching Associate of Biological Sciences, CSU East Bay
2022	Virtual Volunteer Associate Fellow, Microbiology & Immunology,
	Neurobiology and Anatomy, Drexel University College of Medicine
2022	Lab Assistant II of Operations, Roche Diagnostics (Roche Molecular Systems)
2021-22	Formulations Operator II, Robotics, Thermo Fisher Scientific
2020	Research Assistant of Physiological Sciences, Toxicology, University of Florida
2019	Manufacturing Associate Technician, Custom Primers, Thermo Fisher Scientific
2018	Client Relationship Manager, Poshprofiles
2015-16	R&D Coordinator, dosist
2015	Assistant General Manager, Amoura International Inc.
2014	Research Assistant of Anesthesia/Neuroanesthesia, UCSD SoM
2013	Research Assistant of DTMMMP, JABSOM
2012-13	Biology Assistant of DTMMMP, JABSOM
2011	Teaching Assistant of Chemistry, University of Hawaii at Mānoa

SCHOLARLY PUBLICATIONS:

Peer Reviewed Publications: *Co-Authors

- 1. **D.J. Gomez***, T.H. Mulherkar*, G. Sandel, P. Jain*, Co-infection and cancer: Host-Pathogen Interaction between Dendritic Cells and HIV-1, HTLV-1, and Other Oncogenic Viruses. *Viruses*. 2022 Sep 14;14(9):2037.
- 2. **D.J. Gómez*.** Untangling the Microscopic World of Organelles, Cells, Tissues, and Organs: A Focus on the Dysfunctional Golgi Apparatus in Disease Research. *Biology and Life Sciences Forum*. 2023

Non peer-reviewed journal articles

1. D. Gomez*, Pioneering Organelle Structural Biology: Golgi apparatus dysfunction in

Parkinson's Disease, Neurodevelopmental Disorders, and Cancer. *Preprints*, 2022, 2022100383.

2. **D. Gomez*.** Unraveling the Structural Dynamics of Human Pegivirus-1 RNA- Dependent RNA Polymerase Using Computational Methods. *ResearchGate*, 2022.

CONFERENCE ABSTRACTS

1. **Gomez D.J.**, Mulherkar T., Sandel G., Jain P. "Co-infection and cancer: Viral oncogenesis in humans result in liver, blood, and brain cancer by host-pathogen interactions" 12th Annual American Association Cancer Research, Japanese Cancer Associate (AACR-JCA) Joint Conference. (2022)

SYMPOSIUM POSTERS

1. **Gomez D.J.**, Mulherkar T., Sandel G., Jain P. "Co-infection and Human Cancer: Viral Oncogenesis leads to Host-Pathogen-Tumor-Body Interactions" 22nd Microbiology Student Group Symposium in Krutch Theater at Clark Kerr UC Berkeley Campus (2023)

GRANTS

Prior Funding

Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program (UROP)

04/22/2013 Office of the Vice Provost for Research and Scholarship (OVPRS)

University of Hawaii at Manoa

John A. Burns School of Medicine (PI: Bruce Shiramizu)

Role: Co-Investigator

IL-17 Production in CNS by Infiltrating T Cells and Glial Cells in the HIV-1-Infected Brain

The goal of this study to gain mechanistic insights into fronto-striatal brain wiring of neuroinflammatory pathways in HIV-Associated Neurocognitive Disorders (HAND) for the purpose of overcoming translational mental health roadblocks in precision medicine.

EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITES

Teaching

Classroom Instruction

Cal State East Bay

Fall 2022 BIOL 230 (Clinical Microbiology) – 2 sections

Fall 2022 BIOL 270 (Human Anatomy & Physiology I) – 1 section

University of Hawaii at Manoa

Spring 2011 CHEM 161L (General Chemistry I Laboratory) – 2 sections

Modesto Junior College

Summer 2005 English Language – Thailand, Laos (Study Abroad)

Tutoring

2011 Private Organic Chemistry Tutor

2011 Chemistry, Biology, Organic Chemistry (Learning Emporium) *Mentoring (Advisees)* — *Graduate Students* Daniil Mudroy, Cell and Molecular Biology, BS, CSUEB 2022 Biochemistry, Next-generation sequencing, Pharmacogenetics Now at MEDGENOME, Genentech, Biochemistry MS Student at St. Joseph's *Mentoring (Advisees)* — *Undergraduate Students* 2023 Andreea Radu, Nursing Program, (CSUEB) Premed; Pathophysiology; Pediatrics 2023 UF Minority Health Professional Mentorship Program (MHPMP) Emmanuel Espinoza, Biochemistry, University of Florida (UF) Inorganic chemistry; Quantitative Chemistry, Biochemistry 2022 Courtney-Jane Lopez, CNA, Pre-Nursing (CSUEB) Clinical Microbiology; Nursing 2022 Anika Acharya, Pre-Nursing (CSUEB) Human Anatomy and Physiology; Nursing 2022 Yongtao Guan (Pre-med, CSUEB, Ohlone College) Clinical Microbiology; Nursing Workshops/Seminars/Users' Meetings/Symposiums/Conferences/Series AI in IO: Computational Immuno-oncology SITC-NCI Webinar Series 05/24 05/24 2nd Annual Stanford RNA Program Symposium, Stanford Medicine Pediatric & Maternal Innovation Showcase 2024, Stanford Medicine Children's 04/24Health 03/24 Metabolic Health Center Annual Symposium, Stanford National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) 75th Anniversary Symposium 03/24 NIMH's symposium Amplifying Voice and Building Bridges: Towards a More **Inclusive Future** 11/23 IEDB Virtual User Workshop. La Jolla Institute for Immunology. Immune Epitope Database and Analysis Resource 09/23 Beyond blotting: Boosting protein analysis with cell-based immunofluorescent assays 09/23 Stanford Genetics Structural Variants and DNA Repeats 05/23Image Processing for Cryo-EM at S2C2-Stanford-Cryo-EM Center (SLAC) 5th Annual Cal State East Bay Hack Day (Hack the Outbreak) 10/22 10/22 IEDB Virtual User Workshop. La Jolla Institute for Immunology. Immune Epitope Database and Analysis Resource. Funded by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID) Predicting cancer immunotherapy response by highly multiplexed tumor 09/22

00/00	imaging (Certified)
09/22	SSRL/LCLS Users' Meeting (Stanford-SLAC)
06/22	UW-Madison, 42 nd Steenbock Symposium, "Opening Doors to Cryo-EM"
0.7/0.0	Titan Krios G3 and G4 workshop, Cryo-electron tomography, SerialEM.
05/22	Invited Speaker, CSU Northridge, "Data-Driven Discovery of
	Computational Oncology and Modern Molecular Biology"
Profession	al Societies
2024-	Society for Immunotherapy of Cancer (SITC)
2023	Genetics Society of America (GSEA)
2023-	American Society of Human Genetics (ASHG)
2022-	ISCB: International Society for Computational Biology
2022	ACA: The Structural Science Society
2022-	American Associate for Cancer Research (AACR)
2022	Society for Neuro-Oncology (SNO)
2022	American Society for Virology (ASV)
2020	American Society Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (ASBMB)
2013	The American Association of Immunologist (AAI)
2012	Society of NeuroImmune Pharmacology (SNIP)
RECOGIN	NITION
Invited Tal	lks, Panels
04/23	Speaker, Grand Slam Graduate Research Presentation, "Virophysics and
	Structural Dynamics of HPgV-1 NS5B Using Computational Methods,"
	Hayward, CA
03/23	Speaker, Cells 2023 Conference of MDPI/sciforum, "Pioneering organelle
	structural biology: Golgi apparatus dysfunction and cascades of fatal
	pathways in cancer," Virtual.
01/23	Speaker, Drexel Medicine, "Landscape of myeloid and astrocyte
	phenotypes in acute MS lesions and future technological directions,"
	Virtual. (Jain Lab)
10/22	Speaker, Chemistry 2022: Global Virtual Summit on Chemistry &
	Pharmaceutical Chemistry, "Ribozyme mechanisms and Clinical Gene
	Therapy," Virtual.
10/22	Speaker, Cancer Webinar 2022: 5th International Webinar on Cancer
	Research and Oncology, "A human retrovirus in Neuro-Oncology,
	interventional conductome studies, and theranostics in Nuclear
	Medicine," Virtual.

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

Data Science & Analysis in Omics

- Biomedical Data Science
- Data Analysis

- Computational Biology
- Bioinformatics
- Bioimage Informatics

- Integration of Omics Data
- Precision Medicine
- Spatial Omics
- Single-cell Analysis

Biological Understanding

- Molecular Cell Biology
- Neuroscience
- Immunology
- Exercise Biology
- Physiological Sciences
- Cellular-level Understanding

- Deep Profiling and Multiomics
- Multimodal DL/ML
- Predictive modeling
- Data integration
- Spatial Biology
- Biomarker Discovery
- Genetics and Genomics
- Developmental Biology
- Embryology (Maternal-Fetal Interface)
- Aging
- Cancer Biology

OTHER PROFESSIONAL ACCOMPLISHMENTS Oral Presentations

leukemia virus integration.

10/22	Microbiology Control, Microbiology & Immunology, Neurobiology &
	Anatomy, Drexel Medicine, Philadelphia, PA; Gomez D.J. Cancers:
	PCNSL outcome in EBV+/HIV Coinfection and HTLV connection in
	HIV/AIDS patients.
10/22	California State University, East Bay, Hayward, CA; Gomez D. HTLV-1: From
	neuroimaging to neurosurgery and biomarkers of neuroinflammation and
	neurodegeneration in HAM/TSP progression.
10/22	Hack the Outbreak. California State University, East Bay, Hayward, CA;
	Gomez D. PathAR.
09/22	California State University, East Bay, Hayward, CA; Gomez D.
	Deltaretrovirus: HTLV.
09/22	California State University, East Bay, Hayward, CA; Gomez D. "An
	intasome story: Structural basis of host protein hijacking in human T-cell

Certifications

2024	Fundamentals of Data Science in Precision Medicine and Cloud Computing
2023	SSRL RapiData 2023: Data Collection and Structure Solving: A Practical Course
	in Macromolecular X-Ray Diffraction Measurement (Stanford/SLAC)
2022	Predicting cancer immunotherapy response by highly multiplexed tumor
	imaging
2022	Cyber Security for Lab Users, SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory
2019	IRB Training
2019	Life Sciences Responsible Conduct of Research Course (RCR)
2018	Medical School Pathology (192 hours)
2017	Python for Data Science and Machine Learning Bootcamp
2017	Data Science and Machine Learning Bootcamp with R